Guide to the French transvestite postcards, circa 1900-1930.
French transvestite postcards
- Series III. Humor and Other
  - "La Bretagne pittoresque: La Plus belle fille de Pont-Aven", Dated, postmarked 1915; 167 (Folder 17)
    Photographer: A. Waron
    City: "Saint- Brieuc"
    Inscription: "Addressed to Monsieur Dumont; signed Horace (?). Message refers teasingly to representation of gender on postcard: “Comment-latrouves tu ?”"
    Notes: "Older man with gray hair and handlebar moustache dressed in the traditional garb of a woman from Brittany, including a bigouden (starched lace headdress), and with a market basket on one arm and an umbrella under the other. Suggesting the popularity of such images, the postcard echoes the representation of a peasant woman in La Plus Sérieuse des Lorientaises, a card already held by Cornell. Postage stamp and postmark on upper left corner of recto. Photo: Cartes01"
  - Costumes poitevins, Dated 1909; 168 (Folder 17)
    Printer/Publisher: "N. Alix, Pap.- Tab.-Journaux (i.e., Papeterie- Tabac- Journaux)"
    City: Niort
    Inscription: "Addressed to Mademoiselle Gratecap. Brief message (“Affecteux souvenir”) with illegible signature."
    Notes: "Couple dressed in quaint traditional garb of the Poitou region on the west coast of France: One is a man dressed as a man, the other a man cross-dressed as a woman. Scuff to upper right corner of recto. Photo: Cartes01"
  - [Les Deux Gosses], Dated, postmarked 1910; 169-171 (Folder 17)
    Printer/Publisher: "AS with a graphic fleurde- lys between the letters"
    Inscription: "Addressed to Paul Rabeau; messages with three different largely illegible signatures."
    Notes: "Three postcards (nos. 2, 3 and 4) from a series of unknown length recounting episodes adapted from the melodramatic novel Les Deux gosses (Jules Rouff & Cie., 1880) by the popular author and playwright Pierre Decourcelle (1856– 1926). The “two kids” of the title are Fanfan, the son of a diplomat carted off and raised by a married pair of petty criminals, and Claudinet, the ragged natural son of the couple. Decourcelle subsequently adapted the novel as a drama; in an 1896 production at the Théâtre de l’Ambigu in Paris, the characters of the two boys were cast as trouser roles for young actresses, with Fanfan played by Mlle. Mélo and Claudinet by Mlle. Reyé. In the postcard series, the models for the two boys likewise are cross-dressed young women dressed. The images may therefore represent an actual stage production—or at least an expectation established by stage productions that Fanfan and Claudinet would be trouser roles. Stamps and postmarks on recto of each card. Lower corners of one card creased. SOURCE: “A l’Ambigu. Les deux gosses, drame de M. Pierre Decourcelle; Aux bouffes. Ninette. Opéra-comique de Ch. Lecoq et de Ch. Clairville” (page from the Journal Amusant, undated issue from 1896); posted on Europeana; consulted Oct. 31, 2014: www.europeana.eu/portal/record/9200365/ BibliographicResource_1000055735940.html Photo: Cartes01"
  - "Melle (Deux-Sèvres)— Paysanne poitevine. Ringearde partant pour le marché en ville.", circa 1900; 172 (Folder 17)
    Photographer: Jules Robuchon
    City: Poitiers
    Inscription: "Addressed to Mademoiselle Legras Nadel. Brief message on recto (“Cordial Bonjour — Amitiés — Bonne Santé”) with illegible signature scrawled over head of model."
    Notes: "Comic postcard of older man cross-dressed in the traditional garb of a Poitevin peasant woman, putatively from the rural commune of Melle. (The town is now best known as the birthplace of Ségolène Royal, socialist candidate for president in 2007 and now a cabinet minister.) Yellowing to margins and verso (stain from the postcard having been stored in an album with pages with die-cut windows); minor ink offsetting from postmarks."
  - La Mérine à Nastasie, Postmarked 1906, 1909; 173-174 (Folder 17)
    Printer/Publisher: "CCC&C in a trefoil logo"
    Inscription: "Addressed to Monsieur Rochabrun and Maxime Belliard; one is signed E.G. and the other A.D. Brief manuscript messages on the verso of both postcards. brief manuscript message on the recto of one card"
    Notes: "Series of two postcards representing scenes and characters from La Mérine à Nastasie (1902), a play by Yann Saint- Acer, written in the Saintongeais dialect of the west coast of France. The female characters—homely women in folk garb including exaggerated headgear—are played by young men. One card has a postage stamp and postmark on the recto. Photo: Cartes01"
  - Mme Pipelet, "Postmarked 1904"; 175-177 (Folder 17)
    Photographer: Clayette
    Printer/Publisher: "Possible publisher’s logo: White star at lower left right of each photo"
    Inscription: "Addressed to Louise Hautain. Brief, unsigned note in upper margin of recto of each card."
    Notes: "Series of three postcards representing humorous scenes from the daily life of a frumpy old lady played by a cross-dressed older man with a expressively rubbery face and a quite large nose. The illustrations may portray a comic character created by writer Ferdinand Gaultier in such theatrical pieces as Mme Pipelet millionaire, scene de grande bouffe (1861). Postage stamp and postmark on verso of each card. On recto of one card, one word is scratched off of message in upper margin with minor loss to background of photo. SOURCE: Théâtre-Beaumarchais. Mme Pipelet millionaire, grande scène bouffe. Paroles de Ferdinand Gaultier. Exécutée par Bartholy (1861); full text posted on Gallica; consulted Oct. 31, 2014: http://gallica.bnf.fr/ ark:/12148/bpt6k55655464"
  - "Recette Friandises: Gâteau suisse", circa 1900; 178 (Folder 18)
    Printer/Publisher: "A. Bergeret et Cie."
    Inscription: Addressed to Auguste Morel
    Notes: "Woman dressed as a chef wearing a toque, men’s coat and men’s 18th-century kneepants and hose while holding up a fluted cake pan. She leans against a decor suggesting a country kitchen; in the background is a studio backdrop of clouds. Printed in red at the bottom of the recto is a recipe for Swiss cake. Undivided verso with printed heading (“Carte Postale / Ce côté est exclusivement réservé à l’adresse”). Margins moderately worn; minor scuffs and scattered spotting to recto; light foxing to verso. Photo: Cartes03"
  - La Berceuse du gosselin. Je vous présente La Nourrice et le Gosselin, circa 1905; 179 (Folder 18)
    Printer/Publisher: ELD
    Inscription: In pencil on lower margin of recto: François Simon
    Notes: Middle-aged man holding a porcelain doll and dressed as a nanny in a lace cap and apron. Divided verso.
  - Type marseillais, Postmarked 1904; 180-184 (Folder 18)
    Photographer: F. Lacour
    City: Marseilles
    Inscription: Four addressed to Madame C. Couderc; one to Mme Veuve Couderc. The two postcards with divided versos include messages, both with the salutation “Ma bonne amie”; one is signed “ED.”
    Notes: Series of five real-photo comic postcards depicting a plain middle-aged man cross-dressed to represent ordinary women of Marseilles. Each card has a humorous caption giving a line of dialog in the local patois laced with Provençal expressions. Two of the cards (numbered 366 and 367) show a woman wearing a brooch, pearls and an apron. Three (numbered 370, 373 and 374), subtitled “Une Poissonière,” show a fishwife standing in cocky poses while carrying a scale for weighing her goods. Three with undivided verso; two with divided verso. Minor soiling and staining to rectos.
  - [Woman Dressed as a Soldier], circa 1915; 185 (Folder 18)
    Medium: Black-and-White Real Photo
    Notes: Real-photo postcard of a young woman dressed in a World War I soldier’s uniform but with women’s high-heeled bottine-type shoes. The subject has a pipe clenched in her mouth and is sitting on a bench in a courtyard. Divided verso with heading “Carte Postale.”
  - Fils à papa, 186 (Folder 18)
    Inscription: Message on verso addressed to "Mon cher Pierre" and signed "Jeanne."
    Medium: Black-and-white collotype
    Impersonator: Male impersonator
    Notes: Novelty card montage of three photos of the same woman dressed in top hat, tails and knee britches gesturing to a rabbit sitting next to her on a bench. May represent a musical hall trained animal act. Divided verso.
- Costume Series
  - [Couple in Fancy Dress], circa 1905; 187 (Folder 19)
    Inscription: In pencil on verso: “L161”
    Notes: Real-photo postcard of a middle-aged woman dressed as an 18th-century male aristocrat and a younger woman dressed in an 18th-century-style summer gown. The two women are standing side by side, holding hands in a garden setting. Divided verso.
  - [Three Musketeers and Gardener], circa 1905; 188 (Folder 19)
    Notes: Real-photo postcard of four women: three dressed as 17th-century musketeers and one dressed as a male gardener wearing a work apron and heavy clogs and holding a rake. The two women at the center are the same one who appear in the “Couple in Fancy Dress” postcard, and they are standing in the same garden. Divided verso (printing matches the postcard above).
  - [A Gendarme, a Magistrate and Others], circa 1905; 189 (Folder 19)
    Inscription: In pencil on verso: “L129”
    Notes: Real-photo postcard showing six women posing in front of the entry to a brick building. Three are dressed in the simple outfits of working women, including one wearing a long white apron; the other three are cross-dressed as men: a gendarme in uniform; a judge in robe, collar and chapeau; and one in a frock coat and fedora.
  - [Posing With a Touring Car], circa 1905; 190 (Folder 19)
    Inscription: In pencil on verso: “L152”
    Notes: Real-photo postcard showing nine men posing in front of an open touring car on an estate with trees and buildings in the background. The man at the center is dressed as a grand society woman in a travel outfit including a heavy coat, flowered hat, fur muff and pocketbook. The men surrounding her are dressed in various costumes, including one likely as a chauffer, one as a butler with feather duster, one with a crêpe-de-chine false beard, and others in worker’s coats and caps. Divided verso (printing matches the two postcards above).
  - [Men in 17th-Century Costumes], circa 1905; 191 (Folder 19)
    Inscription: In pencil on verso: “L36”
    Notes: Real-photo postcard showing eight men in 17th-century costumes, including two cross-dressed as women: one as a saucy maiden and one as dowdy matron. All are posed in front of a brick wall in a garden. Divided verso (imprinted with a logo of a horse’s head framed by a horse shoe).
  - [Men in Various Costumes], circa 1905; 192 (Folder 19)
    Photographer: E. Lasseron
    Inscription: In pencil on verso: “L106” an “Marqué d’une croix, / [illegible]”
    Notes: Real-photo postcard showing ten men in a variety of costumes, including four dressed as women in dresses and wigs. All are posed in front of an exterior wall. Divided verso (imprinted with a logo of a horse’s head framed by a horse shoe above a star).
  - [Flamenco Dancers and Aristocrats], circa 1905; 193 (Folder 19)
    Inscription: In pencil on verso: “L129”, “57” and “4604”
    Notes: Real-photo postcard showing five men in costume, including two as a male-female couple of flamenco dancers and two as a male-female couple of 18th-century French aristocrats.
- Historical Illustrations: Joan of Arc
  - "Arrivé à Chinon, va droit au roi…", circa 1905; 194 (Folder 20)
    Inscription: "Addressed to Lucien Renault; signed “Ta soeurette [illegible]”"
    Notes: "Historical scene showing Joan of Arc telling the dauphin of France that he will be crowned king at Reims. As is conventional for iconography of Joan during her period of combat, she wears men’s clothing—in this case, an elaborate doublet and riding boots. Conversely, this image steps outside the convention by including a halberd-bearer accompanying Joan; the footsoldier is played by a young woman dressed in a doublet and man’s cap (but wearing quite feminine-looking pumps rather than military footwear). Including an additional cross-dressed character brings this image closer to the genre of trouser roles and gallant scenes."
  - "Jeanne d’Arc. Délivrant Orléans…", "Postmarked 1903"; 195 (Folder 20)
    Inscription: "Addressed to Jeanne Carlin. Brief unsigned message on recto."
    Notes: "Joan of Arc in a doublet, breastplate and helmet, holding a sword and battle standard against a smoky background. A doggerel verse printed in red at upper left on the recto recounts her victory over the English. Undivided verso. Postage stamp and postmark on verso."
  - Jeanne d’Arc, "Postmarked 1903"; 196-204 (Folder 20)
    Notes: "Complete series of eight postcards portraying key moments in the history of Joan of Arc, with particularly high production values and tasteful, understated color tinting including judicious use of gold highlighting. Each card has a caption indicating Joan’s presence at a particular place, along with a date and, in two cases, a brief tagline (from “Jeanne d’Arc à Dorémy / Jeanne entend les voix en 1425” to “Jeanne d’Arc brulée vive à Rouen / 30 Mai 1431”). The series represents Joan’s shift in gender presentation as a crucial framing device for her extraordinary story: The first postcard shows her dressed as a simple shepherd girl hearing mystical voices; the next five show her as the savior of France dressed in full armor, with a sword and battle standard, but with the long hair of a woman; the seventh shows her “devant ses juges” wearing a simple man’s doublet; and the final card shows her forcibly returned to women’s clothing, wearing a white gown while tied to the stake and licked by flames. Photo: Cartes01"
- Swedish Music Hall and Theater
  - Damimitatör John Grafton, circa 1910; 205 (Folder 21)
    Performer: John Grafton
    Photographer: O. Hertzberg (Värnamo, Sweden)
    Printer/Publisher: Svenska Litografisk
    City: Stockholm
    Notes: A rather plain music-hall female impersonator with little makeup, but an elaborate off-the-shoulder showgirl dress. Divided verso.Minor staining to upper margin of recto.
  - John Grafton Damimitatör, postmarked 1912; 206 (Folder 21)
    Photographer: Oscar Hertzberg
    Inscription: Recto: Brief note in Swedish on lower margin. Verso: Addressed to “Bevärignrekryten Herr Gustaf Nicklasson” and with a message in Swedish signed “Justina C. Svenson”
    Notes: Grafton still looking plain—and still hiking up a fancy showgirl dress to display ankles and a bit of leg.Divided verso. Stamp and postmark on verso. Addressed to a “military recruit” in Germany.
  - John Graffton, Krinolinparodist, circa 1910; 207 (Folder 21)
    Inscription: Penciled note on verso: "Double --> DAN"
    Notes: Swedish music-hall female impersonator John Grafton in a comic pose: tying on a kerchief and mugging a broad smile. Divided verso.